[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome back
to EnglishPod. My name is Marco.
My name is Katherine and today
we're talking about things at the office.
That's right we are
at the office but this
time we are going to ask our
boss or manager for a raise.
All right so what
is this word raise?
Let's take a look at it in
today's vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview.
All right so we're going to
ask for a raise so if you are at
your office and you talked to your boss and
you say I want a raise what does that mean?
That means I want more money. Okay
so I want a raise or increase in my salary.
That's right so a raise
is a thing that you
ask for and in this case
a raise means that you
already work at the
company. You already have a
salary and you want some
more money each month.
Okay so that's what we're
going to be talking about today.
Let's listen to this dialogue.
[Music] Excuse me sir.
May I talk to you? Bill sure
come on in. What can I do for you?
Well sir as you know I
have been an employee of
this prestigious firm
for over 10 years. Yes.
I won't beat around the bush.
Sir I would like a raise. I
currently have three companies
after me and so I
decided to talk to you first.
A raise. Son I would love to give you a
raise but this is just not the right time.
I understand your position and I
know that the current economic
downturn has had a
negative impact on sales
but you must also take
into consideration my
hard work, pro-activeness
and loyalty to this
company for over a decade.
Taking into account these
factors and considering I
don't want to start a brain drain.
I'm willing to offer you a 10% raise
and an extra five days of vacation time.
How does that sound?
Great it's a deal. Thank you sir.
Before you go just
out of curiosity what
companies were after
you? Oh the electric
company, the gas company
and the water company.
All right we're back so
now why don't we take
a look at language
takeaway? Language takeaway.
So the conversation we
just heard is a conversation
between a manager or
a boss and the employee
and the employee says
listen I need to talk to
you about something. I
have been an employee at
this prestigious firm for over 10 years
so prestigious is our first word. Okay.
Prostages is an adjective right?
That's right and it means very
respected, very well-known.
It's steamed that's right so something
that is prestigious has a good reputation.
Like for example some
universities like you
hear all the time about
American universities
like Harvard or Yale which are
considered to be prestigious universities.
Or the Nobel Peace Prize
is a very prestigious award.
Okay so it's an
adjective to describe
something that's respectable
well-known or esteemed as you said.
Exactly. All right and
what's on next word?
Our next one is not
so happy this is what
we've been experiencing
in the global economy
this last year or two. It's
called an economic downturn.
All right so in economic downturn is
something negative as you said so it means
that the economy is
not doing very well.
Right so economy economic
you know what this means
but in this case downturn
is the key part of this
phrase to slow down or
to decrease so a downturn
is a time when less people are making money
and less money overall is being earned.
Okay so an economic downturn.
Very good why don't we move on
to our next word
which is negative impact.
So the thing working here is
the economic downturn and it
has had a negative
impact on our sales, on this
company's sales. So a
negative impact as you know
from the first word
is not a good thing.
Right it's an effect right
and it's effect but that's
negative so it's
not a good effect.
So I could say that Marco
being late has had a negative
impact on your work
lately. Okay or the opposite
now what if something is a
good effect on something.
So Marco your hard work
has had a really positive
impact on this company
lately. All right good
so you can use a negative
impact or a positive impact.
All right. Right so
impact again is just the
effect that something
has on something else.
And while the boss said
that he agrees to give him
a raise because in part he
didn't want to start a brain drain.
What's that? Oh this is a very common
phrase you hear about countries.
They have a brain drain or
they want to avoid a brain drain.
A drain is the part of a
sink or a bathtub where
the water goes down.
Okay. It goes away and so
brain drain means all
the brains or intelligent
people or educated
people leave a country
and go to another country or in this case
leave a company and go to another company.
All right so for example if all
the employees at Apple maybe
they start to quit or they
are they start to move
jobs and start to work for maybe Microsoft
or Google that's a brain drain right.
That's right because you're talking
about a large number of people.
Maybe they're all unhappy because they
say that working at Apple is not very nice.
So they all leave and
go to this other company.
The same is true with countries.
You can have very very well
educated people who
when they stop studying they
want jobs they all
look somewhere else.
They go to America or Mexico
or England. So that's called
a brain drain because
they all go away.
Okay so five great phrases
right there and words for you
well let's listen to this
dialogue again and
we'll be back to take a
look at Fluency Builder.
Excuse me sir may I talk to you? Bill
sure come on in. What can I do for you?
Well sir as you know I
have been an employee
of this prestigious firm
for over 10 years. Yes
I won't beat around the bush.
Sir I would like a race. I
currently have three companies
after me and so I
decided to talk to you first.
A race. Son I would love to give you a
race but this is just not the right time.
I understand your position and I
know that the current economic
downturn has had a
negative impact on sales but
you must also take into
consideration my hard work
pro-activeness and loyalty to
this company for over a decade.
Taking into
account these factors
and considering I don't
want to start a brain drain.
I'm willing to offer you
a 10% race and an extra
five days of vacation
time. How does that sound?
Great it's a deal thank
you sir. Before you go just
out of curiosity what
companies were after you?
Oh the electric company
the gas company and the
water company. This first
phrase in today's Fluency
Builder is one of my
favorites. It's something
that we say often when
we're having a conversation
and we want the other
person to just tell us what
they're talking about.
All right so the guy said
you know what I'm not
going to beat around the bush.
Or you could also
say please don't beat
around the bush. So I'm
not sure where this phrase
comes from but it means
please be direct or I'm
going to be direct I will
not wait any longer to
tell you what I'm talking
about. So if somebody
is beating around the
bush that means they are
not being direct they're not
telling you something immediately.
It's you know like when a person is trying
to think but you know has a hard time and
they're really trying to
explain something but you
know it's just well you
know what I'm talking about
it's like that time with that
thing where he did that.
Okay this is really
annoying I know it's
called beating around
the bush because you just
don't say what you're thinking. Right
exactly so you don't say something directly.
Now our next phrase is to take
into consideration take something
into consideration. Well
this is something that the
young man brings up
when he's asking for a raise
he says you should take
into consideration all of
these great things I do.
This means when you make
your decision I want you
to think about these things.
So consideration
means you're thinking
when you're trying to
make a decision. To consider.
All right so to take something into
consideration or you can just say to consider.
So I'm interested in
buying a new TV but I have
to take into consideration
the fact that I don't
have a lot of money. That means
I probably won't get a new TV.
I have to think about these things when I'm
making my decision. Right okay very good
and our last phrase for
today towards the end the
boss was a little bit
interested in knowing what
happened or which companies were interested
in him so he said just out of curiosity.
So this is something we say when
we don't need to know something
it means that we would
like to know because we're
curious we're interested
but not because I need to
know right away what
companies offer you jobs.
So this is a polite way to ask
why someone did something.
So for example so just out of curiosity
Marco what kind of shampoo do you use?
That is very interesting
knowledge that you want there.
Well obviously I don't
need to know what kind
of shampoo Marco uses
but I'm curious because
maybe I'm going to buy
a new kind of shampoo.
So you can start your
sentence by using this phrase
just out of curiosity.
Just out of curiosity.
It's a great one. Listen for that again as
we listen to today's dialogue one more time
and we'll be back in a moment
to talk about getting raised.
Excuse me sir may I talk to you?
Bill sure come on in what can I do for you?
Well sir as you know I
have been an employee
of this prestigious
firm for over 10 years.
Yes I won't beat around the
bush sir I would like a race.
I currently have three companies after
me and so I decided to talk to you first.
Erase son I would love to give you a
race but this is just not the right time.
I understand your position and I
know that the current economic
downturn has had a
negative impact on sales but
you must also take into
consideration my hard work
pro-activeness and loyalty to
this company for over a decade.
Taking into
account these factors
and considering I don't
want to start a brain drain.
I'm willing to offer you
a 10% race and an extra
five days of vacation
time. How does that sound?
Great it's a deal thank
you sir. Before you go just
out of curiosity what
companies were after you?
Oh the electric company the
gas company and the water
company. All right
we're back so interesting
enough he was he needed
a race not because three
companies wanted to hire
him but because he needed
to pay his bills. Well
this is funny because he's
not talking about
companies that's right who are
offering him jobs. He's
talking about the gas,
the water, the electrical
company. This is a very
funny dialogue but I
think asking for a race is
very hard to do because
you know that your boss is
worried about money or
it's a bad time to ask but
you want to ask because it's important that
you get the right compensation for you.
Right and actually it's important
to have a clear objective
when you want to ask
for a race so more or less
what you want to earn
and but plausible within
the company so you're
not going to ask for a 100%
race right you can maybe
aim for a 5 or 10% and
most likely you'll get it
if you negotiate properly.
That's right and sometimes
a race isn't just about
money you can also like
he did ask for some time
off so he gets some
vacation days or perhaps
some training or bonuses
or a bonus so this all
depends on the kind of
negotiations that you make
but but it's worth it to
ask so please let us know
if you've ever had a good
time or a bad time asking
for a race it can be a very
nerve-wracking experience.
I know personally I'm
very uncomfortable with it
but we're excited to
hear what you have to say
if you have any questions
or comments leave
them for us on our website
www.EnglishPod.com.
All right we'll see you guys there.
Bye everyone.